welcome to this evening celebration of
25 years of prison legal news my name is
Meg fiddler I'm a civilian non-combatant
I'm not a lawyer nor have I ever been a
prisoner annette and soon became friends
with paul right ten years ago when he
was awarded a fellowship by the petra
foundation which I directed the
foundation honored Petra tall Shattuck
who grew up in Germany in the shadow of
the Third Reich came to this country to
work as an au pair and stayed on to
graduate from law school with high
honors while raising a family and to
devote her life as a teacher scholar
lawyer and activists to advancing human
rights when Petra died young and
suddenly in 1983 the foundation was
created to recognize and encourage
unsung individuals who were making
distinctive contributions to the rights
and dignity of others by taking risks
and persevering without the safety net
of personal privilege or institutional
support Paul Wright was named a petrol
fellow for his extraordinary work from
behind bars for 13 years on behalf of
prisoners human rights and civil
liberties in 1973 Petra wrote the
problems I see in America are
fundamentally the problems of a mass
democracy in which people have lost the
feeling that they can influence the
government and in which there's so much
social and racial conflict that it is
very difficult to make the old
mechanisms work still she wrote i
believe that if we work to put our
politics to the test of our ideals and
our values which we spell out so clearly
in the Constitution and the Bill of
Rights
that there would be progress and that's
what we should struggle for right now
I'm honored to introduce someone who has
put his politics to the test of those
ideals and values a friend of prison
legal news tonight's keynote speaker
john kyriacou john is a decorated
veteran of CIA counterterrorism
operations and the only CIA officer with
the guts and integrity to publicly
confirm that waterboarding was used to
torture detainees in the so-called war
on terror for upholding his sworn duty
to support and defend the Constitution
of the United States he served almost
two years of a 30 month prison sentence
John first I'd like to thank Paul right
I guess I knew Paul right before I
actually met Paul right i arrived in in
federal prison in Loreto Pennsylvania in
February of 2013 and after a day or two
in prison I got a nice note from Paul
Wright saying we have this publication
it's called prison legal news here's a
two-year subscription and I figured I
would be in prison about two years I
thought okay well that was nice I'll
send him a thank-you note so I sent him
a thank-you note and then I sat down to
read prison legal news and prison legal
news literally changed the course of my
incarceration it changed the way I
looked not only at my own incarceration
but at the issues of mass incarceration
and what a lot of people myself included
called the prison industrial complex it
opened my eyes to issues that I
otherwise would never have been exposed
to issues as fundamental as those of
civil liberties and human rights
I joked with Paul when we spoke in
Seattle a couple of weeks ago that the
first thing I would do when my prison
legal news arrived was gather about a
dozen different guys in myself and we
would read the news and brief out loud I
would read it out loud about things that
stupid prison guards around the country
have done and gotten themselves into
trouble and we would sit and laugh and
loudly stupid prison guards oh this one
raped a guy in the walk-in freezer and
you know so we would kind of make
ourselves feel better by by jumping on
these prison guards but that that was
just for fun Prison legal news actually
was very was a very serious thing for me
because it showed me what really was the
most important thing not just about the
publication but also about the human
rights defense center I said in Seattle
that I speak a lot all over the country
and I know my my topics well and so I
generally tend to wing it I couldn't
wing it with my Seattle address and I
didn't want to wing it with this address
either and I was thinking to myself well
why is it that I'm so much less
comfortable talking about this issue and
after thinking about it I realized that
it's because this issue is so important
and I think I hadn't really thought
through why prison new legal news was so
important to me personally the
conclusion that I came to was that it's
important because when you're in prison
you really are all alone we may have
friends and relatives on the outside but
in prison life just stand still and it's
like Groundhog Day where every day is
exactly like every other day it doesn't
matter if it's the middle of July or if
it's Christmas your day is going to be
exactly like every other day and you
tend to forget that life on the outside
is continuing to move forward
so it was prison legal news that made me
realize that there is support out there
for people like me there there's an
organization out there that is writing
that is suing that's pursuing activism
on issues that are that are important in
my day-to-day life they're lobbying
prison legal news and human rights
defense center really were our voices on
the outside I can't tell you how many
people don't have confidence in their
own intellect to be able to challenge
either their incarceration or the powers
that be that are that are doing things
like charging them eighteen dollars and
thirty cents or whatever it is for ten
minute phone call for example or giving
them a Chase Manhattan debit card with
their commissary money at the end of
their at the end of their incarceration
but that include fees that are so
onerous that really your commissary
money's going to end up going to chase
manhattan or to the bureau of prisons
but prison legal news understood and
prison legal news was out there telling
people what was happening by way of
background I was incarcerated on the
national security charge I was charged
actually with three counts of espionage
which is one of the gravest crimes that
an American can be accused of when when
we say espionage we conjure up thoughts
of Julia snuffle Rosenberg of spying for
a foreign country of treason in some
cases an espionage charge carries with
it the death penalty I'm a patriot I've
always been a patriot and I took an oath
to uphold the Constitution of the United
States not to cover up the CIA's dirty
little secrets and so I decided in that
19 I'm sorry in 2007 that I was going to
respond truthfully to an ABC News
reporters questions I didn't know what
he was going to ask me I said
expected that he would ask me about
torture and I I decided that if he did I
was going to tell the truth and so in
December of 2007 I gave an interview to
brian ross at ABC News in which I said
three things that utterly changed the
course of the rest of my life I said
that the CIA was torturing its prisoners
I said that torture was official US
government policy not the result of a
rogue CIA officer and I said that the
President had personally approved and
signed of the torture policy I was
immediately referred to the Justice
Department with what's called a crimes
report the CIA complaining that I had
committed a crime believe it or not by
the very end of the Bush administration
the Bush Justice Department decided that
I had not committed a crime but a month
later when barack obama was sworn in as
president he asked eric holder to reopen
the investigation of my interview and so
eric holder's Justice Department charged
me with three counts of espionage one
count of violating the intelligence
identities Protection Act of nineteen
eighty-two I'm only the second American
in history to be charged with that crime
and making a false statement I'm still
not sure exactly what the false
statement was supposed to have been it
was thrown out anyway the Justice
Department asked that I be incarcerated
for 45 years for going on ABC news and
talking about torture they said that I
had revealed top secret code word
information that was declassified solely
for the purpose of prosecuting me and
that information was that after the
September 11th attacks the CIA had a
program to kill or capture members of
al-qaeda top secret
top secret 45 years in prison my
attorneys argued from the very beginning
that I was a whistleblower indeed
there's a legal definition of
whistleblowing it's bringing to light
evidence of waste fraud abuse or
illegality or threats to the public
health or public safety the Justice
Department didn't care and what they did
and I didn't even realize this while I
was going through it I didn't realize it
until I actually read about it in prison
legal news was that they will heap
felony charges on you and then come in
at the very end after you've spent a
million dollars in legal fees and say
all right these five felonies we've
charged you with will drop four of them
if you take a plea and that's why the
Justice Department wins 98.8 percent of
its cases according to ProPublica the
fix is in I decided when I first got to
prison that I would begin writing a blog
I was proud of it it was called letters
from Loreto and it ran on firedoglake
com it caused me absolutely no end of
problems with the prison administration
but believe me I've gone nose to nose
with al-qaeda with Hezbollah with the
Iranians I wasn't going to be afraid of
this warrant of the warden in a in a
low-security prison in central
Pennsylvania so I decided to use PLN and
to quote PLN liberally in my blogs it
was PLN that was raising issues that in
my experience were not part of the of
the public conversation issues like
private prisons issues like gouging
prisoners for the use of telephones as I
mentioned earlier issues like video
visits taking the place of real human
interaction with your family or with
your friends
I figured pln was manned by like-minded
people and I wanted to get to know these
people I wanted to work with him with
them not just Paul although I you know
because of the letter and and reading
peel and I was aware of Paul but it
wasn't just Paul it was the entire staff
it was the entire organization these
were good people I also really like the
fact that that pln didn't ignore the
smaller issues the more parochial issues
it's easy to be academic and to talk
about these broad themes of justice and
human rights that's great it's important
but pln also talked about things like
crooked cops which I really didn't know
much about I mean I've seen you know
fort apache the bronx and movies like
that but i didn't have any first-hand
personal experience when it came to to
abusive and sadistic tormenters like we
had in in my own prison there was a book
that i read in prison that was written
actually buy a John J professor peter
moscow's called in defense of flogging
and he argues in that book that the
Federal Bureau of Prisons like all the
state systems really is nothing more
than an employment agency for otherwise
unemployable semi-literate rural white
men and that's why prisons are in the
middle of nowhere because the yoga the
local yokels will just do whatever
they're told to do and they're happy to
have a job it's a federal job it's got a
great pension I'm going to generalize
about something don't think less of me
please this is based on my own
experience they're having a good time
next door to
it was my experience that prison guards
at least at loretto were failed military
grunts people who just couldn't cut it
in the military and had nowhere else to
go they were unable to get jobs with the
local police department and the Bureau
of Prisons came calling in fact many
guards at loretto were second and
third-generation guards people whose
believe it or not their parents and
their grandparents were there and in
some cases were still there can you
imagine three generations of prison
guards working in the same prison I
couldn't fathom the idea so I'm gonna
skip a story that I told in Seattle
about phony tough guys actually I won't
to give it my phone calls were all
monitored in prison monitored in real
time because I was considered to be a
threat to the to the administration my
judge had recommended that I served my
sentence in a minimum-security work camp
and the prosecution agreed to that
stipulation so my attorneys drove me to
prison and drop me off and you know we
all hugged and waved goodbye and I said
you know head held high don't worry
about me guys I'm going to be fine and
they drove away and as they were driving
away the cop that was processing me took
me out and started to take me around to
the back of the prison and I said no no
I'm supposed to be at the camp across
the street and he said not according to
my paperwork you're not I said whoa are
you taking me into the actual prison and
he said yep so i told myself take it
easy there's nothing you can do don't
flip out they'll send you to solitary so
I waited patiently for five days until I
could get a pack number that allowed me
to make a phone
called and I called my attorneys and I
told them what happened and they said
well we could make a motion we can file
a motion to have you moved but we won't
get a hearing for two years at least and
by then you're gonna be home so you're
just gonna have to tough it out and I
thought you know what I'm tougher than
these guys are and I'm gonna make the
most of this and so I started writing my
blog I right here I had my share of
funny tough guys who thought they could
make their bones by taking on the CIA
guy I'm glad to say that I was smarter
than they were a couple of them finally
made their move one mita full of himself
the other got himself suspended there
was one particularly nasty incident
sadistic guard the only one who ever
wore a stab vest but he never bothered
me ever this guy's name was blue at
least that's what we knew him as blue he
was the only guard who used a piece of
electrical tape to cover up his name
because he was such an that he
was afraid somebody would find him on
the outside and get some revenge he was
the also the only guard who wore a stab
vest because he was worried about being
shanked it's a low-security prison
nobody's worried about being shanked but
blue was well I was friendly with the
Italians the Italians when I was in
prison I spent most of my time with them
Italians you may know named Gambino
lucchese Colombo Bonanno good guys so
they actually really were good guys so
one of the Italians uh was chatting with
blue one day and he said blue what unity
working in blue said I'm in central one
and the Italian said oh my friend jon's
in central one and blue said who the CIA
guy I never mess with that guy never and
the Italian said really why not because
blue messed with everybody and he said I
work in this dump for eight straight
hours that's all I need is to go out to
my car at the end of the day
and CNN is standing next to it and I
said to the Italian that's right CNN
will be standing next to his car and
it's going to be in pln and everybody in
the country is going to read it and his
careers toast so he never ever bothered
me one of the things that was a real
shock to me and this too has been
addressed in prison legal news was the
fact that absolutely everything in
prison is is racially based I had never
experienced these these very clear-cut
racial divisions before and I made a
point not to respect them you know in
the TV room for example half of the TV
room is black half of the TV room is
hispanic whites can sit wherever there's
a free speech I mean a free seat but
can't change the channel and pedophiles
aren't allowed in the TV room I made a
point to befriend everybody you know my
own philosophy in life is I like
everybody I meet until they give me a
specific reason to not like them and I
found that that actually worked well for
me in in prison I was in a fortunate
position because I came into prison with
something of a reputation as a human
rights Crusader and the first week that
i arrived in prison two members of the
Nation of Islam approached me well I was
told on my first day by a prison guard
if if anybody walks into your cell
uninvited it's an act of aggression and
you're gonna have to fight so my very
first day I was in prison about two
hours and two Aryans came into my room
swastikas all over their necks the
shaved heads so I jumped up off my bunk
and I said what do you want one of them
said take it easy are you the new guy I
said yeah are you a he says I said
no are you a rat I said no I'm not a rat
I didn't have anybody in my case are you
a chomo I said I don't know what that
means he says chomo like I'm stupid
child molester I said no I'm not a child
molester he said okay then you can sit
with us in the cafeteria oh I guess I'm
with the Aryans now so I was sitting
with the Aryans for quite some time but
in the meantime to members of the Nation
of Islam came up to me and they walked
right into my room they were holding a
newspaper one of them was holding a
newspaper and again I jumped off my bunk
and I said what do you want and he said
you the CIA guy I said yeah he said
Reverend Farrakhan says you're a hero of
the Muslim people and we want to tell
you you're not gonna have any problems
with us I said oh okay great finally one
of the Italians came up to me he was
actually a senior captain in the Bonanno
crime family lived directly across the
the hall from me and whenever i finish a
book or newspaper I'd give it to him I
figure it was good for relations and he
said to me hey let me ask you a question
why do you sit with those Nazi retards
in the cafeteria I said geez I don't
know Pete my first day here they told me
to sit with them he said from today
you're with the Italians I said
fantastic so I was with the Italians
after that well the Italians are the
smallest group in prison but they're the
most highly respected and the reason
they're the most highly respected was
because they get along with everybody
and I decided that that's exactly what I
was going to do when I left prison heck
Paul and I were laughing about this is
in Seattle when I left prison the Crips
and the Bloods had a joint going away
dinner for me it was insane and then the
North dainius the Mexican cartel they
had a burrito dinner for me it's my last
meal in in prison and then the Italians
put on this whole spread they had a
crooked cop on the payroll so we were
getting veal chops and wine and fresh
bread and I told one the Italians I
don't know what your plans are for after
prison but you need to open a restaurant
because
pay $25 for this and he cooked it in a
trash bucket and it was that good anyway
I took pln very seriously I used PLN as
as something on which I could base my
own writings plns focus on human rights
became to me probably the most important
theme that I tried to address in my own
writing when I was on a rotation of the
State Department in the mid-1990s I was
assigned to the American Embassy in
Manama Bahrain it's a it's a very small
country it's the same size and same
population as Pittsburgh and it's in the
Persian Gulf attached to Saudi Arabia by
a long bridge and when I got to Bahrain
in 1994 I got there just in time for the
beginning of an uprising they called it
an Intifada and it was my job as the
human rights officer to document the
Bahraini government's use of force
against unarmed civilians they were also
killing pro texter protesters extra
judicially without the benefit of trial
and they used torture and solitary
confinement against people who had never
been convicted of any crime this was all
documented in my human rights report
which was mandated by by Congress and
was used to pressure the Bahraini
government to respect human rights one
of the things that was very upsetting to
me when I got to prison was the
realization that much of what the
Bahraini government was doing to its
people in the 1990s the American
government does to its people in 2015 we
torture people every day in prisons and
we call it solitary confinement the
United Nations has deemed solitary
confinement to be a form of torture now
we've we've got torture laws in this
country we have the federal torture act
which specifically prohibits torture and
it it actually defines torture well if
you look at the definition of torture in
the federal torture Act
solitary confinement is torture it's not
open for debate it's just tortured plain
and simple the United States is also a
signatory to the united nations
convention against torture not only are
we signatories we wrote the united
nations convention against torture it
also defines torture and we violated
every single day in this country we also
deny prisoners proper medical treatment
this is something that I that I blogged
about quite extensively but my problems
were very very small compared to what
other people go through every day and
again I was in a low-security prison
read pln to see what's going on in our
ad max or supermax prisons it's
unspeakable I wanted to tell you about
one of my cellmates a guy by the name of
James James was on supervised release
and he violated the terms of his parole
just so that he could spend the winter
indoors he was living in a cardboard box
under a bridge in Pittsburgh and it
started to get cold so in October of
2014 he violated just so he could come
back to prison and get a warm bed and
three meals and some medical care so on
his very first day I walked in and he's
just sitting on the bunk and i said hi
are you the new guy he said yeah James
shook his hand um oddball kind of
looking guy about my age long mullet
that went out many years ago he was very
proud of his mullet and he said look I
gotta tell you he said I try to be as
nice a nice a guy as I can be but I'm
severely mentally ill this is exactly
how he said it I'm severely mentally ill
I have paranoid schizophrenia but as
long as I'm on my medication I'm okay I
said all right well I said thanks for
your honesty I'm going home in a couple
of months so please try not to freak out
but otherwise ians is a good room I
think you're going to be
not unhappy here so James got a job in
food service it's the worst job in the
prison especially am food service which
means the cop comes and wakes you up at
4am and you have to go down to the
cafeteria and start cooking the food for
breakfast and and lunch in the meantime
James developed a bleeding hemorrhoid
right so he went down to the medical
unit he said I've got this bleeding
hemorrhoid they gave him tylenol and I
said James you know the time laws aren't
going to help your hemorrhoid so he
filed what's called a BP eight and a
half which is an informal request to
staff to to try to come to a to an
agreement on a complaint if you can't
come to an agreement you file a BP nine
which goes to the warden the BP ten goes
to the regional director and a BP 11
goes to Bureau of Prisons headquarters
in Washington so he complained he said I
have this bleeding hemorrhoid and they
gave me tylenol they told him to go
screw himself so he complained again
instead of doing the nine though he did
an eight and a half in every single day
he would go to the medical unit ask for
something to deal with this hemorrhoid
and they wouldn't give him anything and
he would file another eight and a half
so rather than going up the chain of
command he just kept hitting the same
medical assistant they deemed that to be
a threat to staff and so they came and
cuffed him one day in the cell and they
took him to solitary now as part of his
punishment completely illegal they
decided to completely pull him off his
antipsychotic medications how that's a
legitimate punishment is an utter
mystery to me it's a crime but they got
away with it because who's the court
going to believe these uniformed
officers or this lunatic who's been
living under a bridge in Pittsburgh I
know what happened next because one of
the Mexicans with whom I became friendly
was in the cell next to James in
solitary and he said that every day the
medical unit would send somebody down to
solitary to see if everybody was okay
but they would deliberately skip James's
cell just because he was a troublemaker
and so he was getting more and more
agitated as time was going on finally
one night he sang 99 bottles of beer on
the wall for nine consecutive hours
people wanted to kill him and then he
eventually got up on to his bunk took
off his slipper and hit the sprinkler
with his with his slipper that set the
sprinklers off all over solitary he
flooded solitary I happened to be in the
hall where solitary was when this
happened I didn't realize exactly what
was happening but they pushed all of us
out of the hall and the cops came in
dressed in like this SWAT gear SWAT
outfits all black vests the whole
business and they went into the cell and
they they tased James twice they sprayed
him with pepper spray they cuffed him
but then they stripped him naked and
they took him outside now you've heard
about solitary being 23 hours a day in
solitary well that one hour that's left
over you get to walk around a 10 by 12
foot dog cage in the in the back outside
yourself that's your exercise walking
around this it's literally a giant cage
it's January in central Pennsylvania and
so they take James outside naked and
they leave him there the Mexican he was
telling me the story said that he
started by saying I'm sorry I shouldn't
have done it please let me back in then
he started crying then he curled up into
a ball and then he passed out finally
they brought him back in but for the
rest of his time there he couldn't speak
that's not medical care that's torture
that's abuse and that's not been
reported in the mainstream media the
only place that's been reported not just
James's case but cases like James was in
prison illegal news prison legal news is
the only organization the only
publication that really cares about
these issues they care about mental
health care they care about
pharmaceuticals and and the availability
of pharmaceuticals in prisons nobody
else does so really it's for that reason
that I'm especially proud to be here I
told Paul right in Seattle and I said it
before when we met for the first time in
Washington that I know what the rest of
my life is going to be like it's going
to be it's going to be one of activism
because these are issues that the
American people need to hear about and
they're not hearing about it you know
one article in the in the new york times
magazine every 10 years is not really
furthering the cause it's the human
rights defense center and prison legal
news that are furthering the cause so
thank you for having me thank you for
allowing me to be associated with prison
legal news thanks for coming tonight
it's actually quite a good size crowd I
think Paul would agree and thanks for
listening
you